Individually catalogued manuscripts, 1591-2005 Various call numbers
Lilly Library
- Freddy - Charles E. Pont, 1935
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767915
  Illustrated manuscript of an unpublished juvenile book. The book follows the life cycle of the eponymous Freddy, a green frog, and is dedicated "To Joan and All Boys and Girls who are interested in the preservation of wild life in America". The half-title, illustrated title page, and dedication are drawn in pencil. The text is cut up and pasted down typescript with twenty-seven pencil illustrations are incorporated into the narrative.
- Compendium physicae, 1709-1753
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8251497
  See Vertical File for publication history. Comprising a title page, 240 numbered pages, and a contents page for the Compendium Physicae, and illustrated with diagrams and tables throughout. The last page is signed "Finitum April 15 1710. John Coit." Two additional manuscript texts are included: Of ethicks and its end / Charles Morton (42 p., dated at end: 1710); and, Advice to young ministers / Charles Morton (19 p., dated at end: 1710). There are 3 additional pages of later miscellaneous notes, dated from 1742 to 1753.
- Vorlesungen über die Funktionentheorie, 1896
  Transfer: 2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8895833
  One bound volume of Professor Hilbert's manuscript teaching notes. The year 1896 is based on textual information (see p. 195, which includes a statement about the French mathematician Jacques Salomon Hadamard, who had "just two weeks ago" proved the prime number theorem (1896)); other dates also support 1896: p. 24, "Mo 2 XI" (i.e. Monday, 2 Nov.); p. 40, "Mo 9 XI" (i.e. Monday, 9 Nov.); and, p. 72, "Mo 23 XI" (Monday, 23 Nov.).
- Natural history diary; Essay on fertilization; Flower list, 1903
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10869489
  A unique privately-made manuscript diary (164 written pages) with 55 finely-drawn watercolors illustrating over 230 flowers with their Latin and English names, date and place found, and additional information such as the kind of soil and measurements for each sample. Included are six pages of the taxonomy of the corresponding class and family, with descriptions and characteristics, as well as a full index and map. Also included is a twenty-page essay on fertilization with drawings. In all probability the author was influenced by Elizabeth Twining (1805-1867), who was a celebrated botanical artist from the north of England, and believed botany had a place in the education of women. Woodall's map provides the locations where she found her flora, mainly in Northeast England. The diary records Phyllis K. Jewson Woodall's daily travels in order to find different specimens. She then draws and describes each plant in great detail, illustrating one to a sheet mounted on heavier stock with description on the facing sheet. Her notes describe details after the specimen has been seen under a microscope.
- Carte-de-visite for Louis Agassiz, [ca. 1867?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9154900
  Head and shoulders portrait of 19th century paleontologist/geologist Louis Agassiz, taken when he was about 60 years of age. Image is 93 x 58 mm., pasted to a slightly larger card, with the studio's name printed in brown on the back. Written over the printed name of the studio, "Warren's," in mss. on front below photo: Prof. Agassiz.
- Photograph of John Muir, [1908?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/9154913
  An original sepia portrait photo of an elderly Muir, well-dressed, and examining a flowering plant. Photograph was taken about 1908 (see University of the Pacific, John Muir Papers). Mounted on a slightly larger backing. The photograph is signed "Kraig." The Barry Cassidy Rare Books blog (http://www.facebook.com/note.php?note_id=421643038065, 8/21/10), suggests that this might be one of two Oakland photographers, Albert W. Kraig or Victor Kraig.
- Original drawings of freshwater fish, ca. 1876-1877
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/14154192
  An album of 32 original pencil drawings of freshwater fish by David Starr Jordan, on variously sized sheets of paper, most identified beneath the image, most species found in Georgia. Accompanied by the newspaper clippings that the original drawings were folded in before being placed in the album; also includes dealer's description and an evelope addressed to "Mr. G. S. Myers, Dept. of Zoology, Stanford University, Palo Alto, Calif."
- Autograph receipt signed by George Edwards, 7 Mar. 1747
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8184054
  In this holograph receipt, dated 12 Nov. 1747, Edwards notes that he has received two pounds two shillings from James West (1703-1772) "for [his] second part History of birds."
- Presentation medal depicting Jean-Athanase Sicard, [ca. 1929]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11981377
  Consists of presentation medal depicting neurologist Jean-Athanase Sicard. The front of the medal features engraved image and name of Jean-Athanase Sicard by A. Morlon. The reverse lists, in French, Sicard's achievements in the field of medicine. Medals such as this are normally given as gifts to doctors on graduating from medical school or other important occasions.
- Francis Day volume of annotated medical articles, 1860-1861
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12426907
  Medical artices annotated by Francis Day, with some of his natural history notes. Day commonly had his articles and notes bound up with blank leaves for further annotation. In this volume, the printed Tropical Fevers (originally published in the Lancet and subsequently published in Indian Annals) is bound and extensively annotated and corrected by Day with notes on a preface and dedication. Other notes and articles, transcribed in manuscript and annotated, follow: "Notes on Cochin" Aug. 1-2, 1861; diseases of the liver; dracunculus, or guinea-worm; peenash, or worms in the nose; elephantiasis; berberi (incomplete); vaccination; and ignipeditis, or burning in the feet. When read from the reverse, the volume contains an incomplete article on a type of palsy and notes on natural history.
- Eli Lilly Laboratory notebook, ca. 1908-1910; 2008
  Gift: 20008
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8083563
  Laboratory notebook, ca. 1908-1910, written by Ernest G. Eberhardt. The notebook pages (most of which are handwritten) are not numbered, but have been indexed by Eberhardt's son, Edward Eberhard, numerically according to their first lines (plus second lines in some cases). Accompanying materials include: an Eberhardt family tree (with note dated 2008), photocopies of two articles about Ernest G. Eberhardt, a photocopy of a letter from Eli Lilly to Ernest G. Eberhardt (dated Mar. 18, 1952), and a photocopy of Edward Eberhardt's inventory of the collection (including notes on his father's career).
- Charles S. Wilson day book and ledger, ca. 1856-1869
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8184403
  A holograph day book and ledger ([119] p.), dated 1856-1869, written by Charles S. Wilson in Howard County, Indiana. He records the work on his farm, the workers he hires and their pay. In addition, he tells of his planting and harvesting. Wilson also keeps records of his purchases and tells of going to church camp meetings.
- Star Chamber dinner accounts during the reign of Queen Elizabeth I, 1591 and 1595
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8376776
  See Vertical File for additional information. Two manuscript accounts of Star Chamber dinners, the first of which is: "The expenses of the Dyettes provided for the Queenes most honorable Counsell at her graces Starchamber at Wesm[inster] during the Hillarye Tearme in the year of the Raigne of our most Sov[er]aigne Lady Queen Eliz in the xxvii Anno dm 1590[/1]," specifically for the 3rd, 5th, 10th, 12th, 13th, 27th and 29th of February, 1591, with the names of those who dined on each occasion witten in the margins. The second account is for the six dinners held on the 24th, 29th, and 31st of January and the 5th, 7th and 13th of February, 1594 [i.e. 1595].
- A Declaration of his Maties. [Majesties] fare upon a Flesh-day, 1627
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8184416
  Original manuscript list (in two columns, written on one side only) gives the food necessary for a Fleshday dinner, with prices, and the food for supper, with prices. Among the items enumerated are: mutton, veal, capons, chickens, beef, shoulder of mutton for gravies, turkeys, pigeons, larks, partridges, pheasants, rabbits, tarts, and kid.
- Wagashi illustrations from Meiji period, 1899
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8993873
  An 1899 Japanese manuscript "catalog" containing 18 pages of color paintings of the traditional Japanese confections called Wagashi. Many of the designs mimic such forms as mountains, mushrooms, birds, and a turtle. Some are abstract forms with multiple references while others mimic the art of origami.
- Wire service story of the first hydrogen bomb test, 16 Nov. 1952
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981715
  Wire service copy from United Press International, dated November 16th, regarding the testing of the first hydrogen bomb.
- Rules orders and instructions for the future government of the Office of the Ordnance in England, [1702?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767910
  See Vertical File for bookseller's description. Detailed account of the internal service rules and orders governing the Office of Ordnance in England in the later 17th century written for Christian Lilly. The first part of the manuscript (p. 1-64) is the warrant which established the modern Board of Ordnance in 1683, describing the structure of the organization and elaborating the duties of each of the officers and employees. This is followed by the amendments of James II in 1686, William III in 1689 and 1690, and Anne in 1702.
- Mason Abercrombie Shufeldt illustrated letters, 1882-1883
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8376778
  See Vertical File for bookseller's description. Three holograph "journals" written in the form of letters addressed to Shufeldt's fiancé, Elise, and signed "Mace"; each is sewn in self-wrappers with hand-drawn and colored covers of nautical themes and is numbered on the cover: "Letter No 1," "Letter No 2," and "Number of Letter No 3." The entries describe Shufeldt's travels in detail and his devotion to his "far-off-sweetheart" in depth. Included also are several hand-drawn maps and views throughout the letters. The collection includes the three postmarked mailing envelopes with Miss Elise Buckingham's Zanesville, Ohio, address. A holograph letter from Buckingham to Shufeldt, dated March 7, 1883, breaks their engagement; the letter is in a small envelope marked "The Last."
- [The Album of photographs from the cruise of the U.S.S. Enterprise to Madagascar], [ca. 1883?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12539206
  This album contains 49 black and white photographs chronicling the cruise of the USS Enterprise to Madagascar (rest of the pages of the album are blank); includes a holograph list of the photographs (2 folded leaves ([4] p.)). The USS Enterprise, a barque-rigged screw sloop, was launched 13 June 1874 at Portsmouth Navy Yard, Kittery, Maine, USA, by John W. Griffiths, a private contractor; and commissioned 16 March 1877, Commander George C. Remey in command. She was later commanded by Bowman H. McCalla around 1890. Recommissioned on 12 January 1882, the USS Enterprise cruised the east coast until 1 January 1883 when she sailed on a three-year hydrographic survey that took her completely around the world. The findings on this cruise added materially to the knowledge of the oceans, their currents, and their bottoms. Enterprise was decommissioned at New York on 21 March 1886.
- Isaiah Thomas letter, 20 Oct. 1790
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8114714
  One page holograph letter signed, lacking the integral address leaf, written at Worcester to Mr. Leffingwell, thanking him for his letter of the 12th and for sending Dr.Langdon's subscription paper.
- Thomas Fleet note, 7 Mar. 1792
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8184404
  A short note written by Thomas Fleet to "Mr. Rogers," marked Boston, March 7, 1792. In the note, Fleet directs Rogers to "deliver to the Bearer the one half Barrell of the superfine Flour, you mentioned yesterday," on his account.
- Bought of James Keating, bookseller stationer & printer, 1763-1764
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8235574
  A partially printed receipt (1 leaf ([2] p.)) with a holograph list of the books (and their prices) noted, dated 1 August 1763, and signed by James Keating. The printed portion, which reads, "Stratford, 176_, Brought of James Keating, Bookseller Stationer & Printer," is engraved. The bill was marked as paid on 14 May 1764.
- George Washington pass forgery, [1830-1869?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11981382
  Forgery consist of a short permission note supposedly written by George Washington on September 12th, 1780.
- Forgery of Walt Whitman autographed letter, [1930-1935?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11981391
  Forgery consists of short letter from supposedly from Whitman dated for Apirl 3, 1891.
- A Breif [sic] of the charges of the household for vij years with the difference of sommes, 156-?
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8260620
  Mid-16th century Latin manuscript leaf (marked as "i" on verso) summarizing household accounts for the entertainment expenses (totalled) for the years 1539-1560 during the reigns of four sovereigns: Henry VIII (1539 and 1540), Edward VI (1550), Mary I (1556 and 1557), and Elizabeth I (1559 and 1560). The emphasis in the accounts is on household and food expenses.
- Four poems: Malacoda, 2009
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8091273
  A unique artist's book by Pontus Carle, with his original painted, textile and paper collages coupled with the hand lettered text includes the poem, Malacoda (from Echo's bones, and other precipitates, 1935). Bound in blue boards, hand lettered on cover.
- Chinese and English dictionary, 1818-1819; Bound in modern three quarter calf, marbled boards. [350] p.; 26 cm. (Call number PL1455 .W79)
  James Winthrop (1752-1821), the translator/compiler, is sixth generation of John Winthrop, first governor of Massachusetts. He graduated from Harvard University in 1769 and assumed the duty of librarian in 1772. He was a founding member of the American Academy of Arts, a Judge of Common pleas in Middlesex, Mass., and a founder of the Massachusetts Historical Society. Although his primary interest was in the interpretation of biblical prophecies, Winthrop was also interested in philology and languages. His friendship with William Bentley and Timothy Alden induced him to leave his extensive library, which was in its day one of the best private collections in Massachusetts, to Allegheny College, of Meadsville, Pa.
  Binder's title.
  Bound with: Locke, John. Common place-book, on the principles practiised by John Locke esq. New-Haven: Published and sold by Increase Cooke & co., 1804.
  Purchased: 2008